[Music]
what do these diagrams have to do with
the arithmetic mean geometric mean
inequality let's find out
[Music]
start with a right triangle with legs of
length A and B
use four copies of the triangle rotated
so that we create this shape which is a
square with a side length of a plus b
inside there's a missing Square reflect
each triangle about its hypotenuse
creating this diagram using eight
triangles notice there's still a missing
Square inside
[Music]
to verify that this missing inside shape
is a square notice that the side length
can be computed as the difference of the
leg lengths of the original triangle so
we see that the square has a side of
length a minus B
now we can find the area of this shape
in two different ways first we note that
it is an A plus b by a plus b rectangle
so the area is a plus b quantity squared
on the other hand we've used eight
triangles plus the inner Square so we
have an area of eight times a half a B
plus the quantity a minus B squared we
can simplify the eight triangles to have
the area four times a times B now we
note that the quantity a minus B squared
is always non-negative so if we leave it
off we obtain the inequality a plus b
squared is greater than or equal to 4
times a times B
as we vary A and B we see that the inner
Square gets larger and smaller depending
on the sizes of A and B but we also note
that the square is always there except
in the one instance when A and B are
exactly the same so that that square
shrinks to zero area
from this we conclude that we have
equality amongst the inequality if and
only if a minus B is zero so that a
equals B
upon taking square roots and dividing
both sides by 2 we obtain the inequality
a plus b over 2 is greater than or equal
to the square root of a times B this is
the arithmetic mean geometric mean
inequality